Finding Aid for Howard E. Merrill papers, 1917-1924.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Howard E. Merrill papers 1917-1924
Merrill, Howard E.
0.4 linear feet
851818 Aa 2
Papers of a Y.M.C.A. volunteer depicting events following the 1917 October Revolution in Russia, POW camps in Germany, and relief work among Russian refugees in 1920-1924.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Rev. and Mrs. Charles W. Brashares (Donor no. 4605 ) and and Mrs. Russell Leavitt, of Meredith, New Hampshire (Donor no. 4804 ), in 1969
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
This collection has not been digitized by the Bentley Historical Library.
Howard E. Merrill served as a Y.M.C.A. Secretary in Russia during the October 1917 revolution. He provided relief support for Russian soldiers and members of the Allied Expeditionary Force in Archangel until 1919. In late 1920 - early 1921 he served as a War Prisoners Aid Secretary for Russian prisoners in eight POW camps in Bavaria, Wurttemberg, and Brandenburg. After the repatriation of Russian prisoners-of-war, he transferred to the Russian Department to provide welfare services to Russian refugees.
Correspondence of Howard Merrill and some of his wife Edith Merrill with relatives in the United States while stationed and traveling in Russia, Poland, Germany, Latvia, Estonia, Sweden, and --to a lesser extent-- Japan describing social, economic and political conditions, everyday life, and work of the Y.M.C.A. offices and volunteers in these countries. Merrill travelled and wrote about locations in Siberia, Moscow, Petrograd, Pskov, Archangel, Nizhnii Novgorod, Samara, Riga, among other locations.
Correspondence and Y.M.C.A. reports from Germany contain depiction of conditions in German prisoner-of-war camps and Russian prisoners. Russian-language handwritten publications of Russian POWs include playbills and illustrated newsletters.
Papers of Donald A. Lowrie, Y.M.C.A. secretary who served in Russian and Eastern Europe between 1916 and 1932 include his 1920 "Moscow diary" and miscellaneous writings on the subject of Russian prisoners of war.
Subjects:
Merrill, Howard E.; Lowrie, Donald A., (Donald Alexander), 1889-1974; Young Men's Christian Association; Prisoners of war--Germany; Prisoners of war--Russia (Federation); World War, 1914-1918--Russia; World War, 1914-1918--Prisoners and prisons, German.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921; Poland--History--Wars of 1918-1921; Polar Bear Expedition
Contributors:
Lowrie, Donald A., (Donald Alexander), 1889-1974; Merrill, Edith
Genre Terms:
Photographs; Postcards
- Howard E. Merrill papers
  - Correspondence
    - 1917 (Box 1)
    - 1918, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - 1919 (Box 1)
    - 1920 (Box 1)
    - 1921, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1922 (Box 1)
    - 1923-1924 (Box 1)
    - Undated (Box 1)
  - Reports, 1920-1924 (Box 1)
  - Russian prisoners-of-war camp publications
    - Russian Theater playbills, October-December 1920 (Box 1)
    - Newsletters
      - Voskhod (Sunrise), no.1, November 7, 1920 (Box 1)
      - Internirovannyi krasnoarmeets (The Internee Red Army soldier), nos. 1-2, January 1921 (Box 1)
  - Donald A. Lowrie
    - Moscow Diary, November 1920 (Box 1)
    - Writings, 1920 (Box 1)